Your son
소자
Understands
알겠습니다
Good
그래
This Chu Huan is a loyal and righteous man
초환은 충의지사야
Before he goes
죽기 전에
Go see him
한번 만나 봐라
Yes
예
Your Highness
전하
You've come
오셨습니까
Before acting
일을 거행하기 전에
Your subject thought he might lose his head
죽을 각오를 했습니다만
Just didn't think
전하께
It would nearly drag Your Highness down
이렇게 누가 될 줄은 몰랐습니다
Chu Huan
초환
The order was mine
명령은 내가 내렸네
You've followed me since the north
자넨 북방에서부터 날 따랐는데
I
난...
Your subject first followed Your Highness
제가 전하를 따른 건
Only for the prince's salary
녹봉을 받았기 때문이고
Following Your Highness south
전하를 따라 남쪽으로 내려온 건
Was to preserve life and body
그저 목숨을 부지하려던 겁니다
Now your subject
천자를 거스른 죄로
Is guilty before heaven's might
시대의 흐름에 밀려난 죄로
Guilty before the times
스스로 죄인이 된 건데
Why does Your Highness blame yourself?
전하께서 왜 자책하십니까
The high noble families
세도가와 사족들은
Are the mountains connecting all of Jiangnan
강남에 늘어선 산맥과도 같습니다
Both protecting the current Xuan Kingdom
지금의 선나라를 수호하는 벽이기도 하고
And keeping the Son of Heaven
동시에 천자께서
From leaving their shadow
그 그늘 밖으로 나오지 못하게 가로막고 있지요
Your subject
신이
Since I cannot be
비록 산을 가르는 칼이 되지는 못하나
Then to be Your Highness's
전하께서 밟고 나아가실
Stepping stone
벽돌 한 장이라도 될 수 있다면
Is fine
그것으로 족합니다
When we went south
그 옛날 남하할 때
Your subject had family and old friends
신에겐 북쪽에 남겨둔
Left in the north
친지와 벗들이 있습니다
Under your subject
제 부하 중에도
Are many people
저와 같은 처지인 이들이 적지 않습니다
Your Highness once promised me
전하께서는 예전에 저에게
Them
그리고 그들에게
And the millions of northern people
북방의 수많은 옛 백성에게 약속하셨습니다
That one day
언젠가 반드시
We would defeat the Wutu in the north
북방에서 오노를 몰아내고
And recover our land
우리 강산을 되찾겠노라고
Is there anything else
내가 자넬 위해
You need me to do?
마지막으로 할 일이 있느냐?
Your subject has a capable student
신에게 유능한 문하생이 한 명 있습니다
Named Zhu Yuanzhi
이름은 주원지입니다
Please, Your Highness
부디 전하께서
Put him to good use
그를 중용해 주시옵소서
Certainly
꼭 그리하겠네
This half journey
인생의 절반을
To be able to serve Your Highness
전하를 위해
Shelter from wind and rain
비바람을 막고
And block blades
창칼을 물리칠 수 있어서
Is Huan's fortune
영광이었습니다
This cup of wine
이 한 잔의 술은
Your subject
신이
Deserves
받을 자격이 있겠지요
To Your Highness
전하께 올립니다